A Guide to the William W. Thomas Collection, 1971-2008
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
William W. Thomas Collection
1971-2008
Special Collections, James Madison University
SC 5058
13 boxes
The materials presented in this collection are Dr. Thomas’ personal papers extracted from his estate after his death in 2008. These files contain notes from classes, recommendation letters for students, class materials from classes he taught, his personal research and his involvement at James Madison University.
Thomas Estate
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Due to the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 protecting the academic records of students, access to Series 2 is not available to the researchers. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Bridgewater College in 2010
Provenance
Direct transfer of ownership from Bridgewater College after they acquired the collection from the Thomas Estate. JMU staff retrieved the boxes from the Thomas house.
Biographical Information
Dr. William W. Thomas was a professor of Religion and Philosophy at James Madison University from 1971 to 2003 when he officially retired. He was a certified reverend and served as an advisor to Theta Alpha Kappa, Honors Religious Studies Fraternity, and Intervarsity, as well as Phi Sigma Kappa, Philosophy Honors Fraternity. Dr. Thomas received his Bachelor’s degree from Washington and Lee University, where he reached Cum Laude in 1954. He then received his Master’s degree from Yale University in 1957, and his Doctorate from Duke University in 1964. He first began his career teaching at The Linwood Colleges and later taught summer sessions at Bridgewater College. He eventually began his career at Madison College in 1971.
Separated Materials
Adventures of Famous Travellers in many lands: With descriptions of manners customs, and places. New York: WM L Allison Company (1890). G525 .A25 1890
Carlyle, Thomas, Life of Friedrich Schiller 1845. PT2482 .C3 1845
Duntzer, Henrich. The Life of Schiller (London: MacMillan & Co.) 1883. PT2482 .D8 1883
Japp, Alexander Hay, LL. D, German Life and Literature: in a Series of Biographical Studies. (London: Marshall Japp & Company) [1880].PT67 .A2 J3 1880
Morley, Christopher, Don’t Open Until Christmas 1931 January 1. PS3525 .O71 1931
Richter, Jean Paul Friederich, The Campaner Thal and Other Writings. (Boston: Ticknor and Fields) 1864. PT2455 .A13 1864
Smith, Roswell C. English Grammar on the Productive System: A Method of Instruction Recently Adopted... (1867). PE1111 .S65 1867
Scope and Content
The materials presented in this collection are Dr. Thomas’ personal papers extracted from his estate after his death in 2008. These files contain letters for students, class materials, personal research and administrative records from James Madison University.
Arrangement
This collection remains in the same order as it was extracted from Dr. Thomas’ estate in order to maintain significance.
The collection is arranged in six series:
1: Administration
2: Student Relations
3: Miscellaneous I
4: Advisory
5: Classwork
6: Miscellaneous II
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
None
Contents List
- Administration Folder, 1972-1991; 1
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Athletics Academic Banquet, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Retirement Information (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - UTS Luncheon, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eastern Orthodox Patriarch, October 19- November 17, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sacr Coeur (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Christian Psychology (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Phil 101 Blank Test (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - PAC - Nominations for Distinguished Teaching, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Irony vs. Satire (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gospels (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - N.T. Papers, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Test Answer Sheets (Blank) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kingdom of God - Bright (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sample Pieces and Model Papers (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Places for Film Study (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Folder APA, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Special Studies (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dr. Kipple (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Humanities Seminar- Workshop, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - EvaluationMR. MILLER (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Union Seminary, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Promotion of Tenure (Psychology etc.), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Former Student Correspondence, 1977- 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Library Subcommittees Charge, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Theology for Everyday Living (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Teaching (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Library Reserve Lists, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Womens Dancers- Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Isabel Rogers, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Proposal, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bibles (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reading Liked BestBest Books, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Thank You Letter to Students (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Teaching (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Stassen, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dr. Forstman (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Capstone Class, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Speakers- Introductions, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Special Studies, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Careers for Philosophers (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Honor Pledge, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Department Head Activities Survey (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Promotion & Tenure Reports (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Landing a department- Department Head (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Religion is an Illusion (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Dr. Lippke, Promotion & Tenure Report (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Review Religion 101 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bultman: Letter to Sheffield Missien (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Student Relations, 1976-2006; 2
  - Shenandoah Phi Beta Kappa (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Spring 1999 Grades and Evaluations (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Phil 200 Syllabus, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - What it was like Last Semester of Teaching (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Class rolls, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - OT Test #1 (Box 2, Folder 29a)
  - OT Test #2 (Box 2, Folder 29b)
  - OT Test #3 (Box 2, Folder 29c)
  - OT Test #4 (Box 2, Folder 29d)
  - OT Test #5 (Box 2, Folder 29e)
  - OT Final Test (Box 2, Folder 29f)
  - Student Evaluations (Box 2, Folder 29g)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Textbook Orders (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - GPhil 101 Spring, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thanks for Dr. Thomas (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Estate:JMU Related (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Recommendation for Stockton L. Wright (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Drew Thistlethwaite, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Neil W. Moubroy, 2004 November 05 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Ann Payne, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dustin Kidds Thesis, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kansas Gooden- Law School Recommendation (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sarah Davelaar Recommendation, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Joshua R. Hayden Recommendation (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Seth Horrell, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Ms. Heather Lodovico (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - David Bryan, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - David R. Fly, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Spencer Daniel, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Tonya Rowe, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Kristi James, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kevin A. Knight, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Nathan Z. Henkel, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Richard John Gilmartin Jr., 2001 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Todd Witherell, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Jeff Vogel, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Anthony Thomas, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Michael Abalow, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Mike Ball, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Lauren Stanley, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Whitney Mitchell Recommendation, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Rachel Montgomery, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - John Call (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Tom Mirabella, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Ms. Jodi E. Jacoby, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Colin Pine, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Baxley Micelli (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Scott Wells, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Randy See, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Robert Flory, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Bobbi Jo Dean, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Jeremy Kent, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Jason Fountain, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Ken Christian, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - David A. Beer, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Anne Schouw, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Kevin Kim, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Sam DelVecchio, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Kyle Kockler, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Jason Sitterson, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Chris Etheridge, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Stephen Jordan, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Jessie Suplizio, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - John Nah, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Paul O. Kim, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Wendy Dyal, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Brian Bradford, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Derek Lam, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Judd Berube, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Anna Montgomery, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Brian Hamrick, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Dr. McFadden, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Tim Reynolds, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Recommendations (Student) Krisztian Horvath, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Recommendations to Write (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Craig Bittenbender, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jeremy Seuss, Mailed 1996 February 12 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Michael Abelow, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tim Johnson, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Matt Beland, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ivan Riley, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Megan Malarkey, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Angel Johnson, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - David R. Lapp, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Blair Burns, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - C.J. Goella, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Michelle Moyer, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lisa Binhammer, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Recommendations (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Recommendations (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Recommendations, 1976-1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations, 1984-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous 1, 1991-2001; 3
  - Evil Genius, Demon, God of Disaster (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - John Locke, Kant, Berkeley, Descartes (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Pieces of Lecture (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Jeremy Bentham and Mill (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Syllabus, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Notes for Lectures (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Jean Paul Satre (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pascal, Rousseau, Social Contract, More Philosophers (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Schopenhauer, The Apology, Euthyphro (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Philosophy and Literature, Every authentic work of literature (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Dr Thomas writings from 1992 and notes (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Introduction and Outline (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Albrecht Ritschl: The Doctrine of Sin (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Note from Steve, Schleiermacher Lecture, Phil-Religion 375, Spinoza, Introduction (An Meine Studenten) (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Notes for Lectures (Schleiermacher, Achs Speeches) Speech onOctober 16, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Dustin Kidd Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Summary Listing of Topics Considered Important by some Harrisonburg and Valley Residents (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Christian Ethics (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Loose Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Addresses (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Advisory, 1978-1998; 4
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Retirement Miscellaneous Documents (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Membership List: Theta Alpha Kappa (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Charge, Theta Alpha Kappa, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Notice, Invitation to Faculty, students (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Luncheon Seating (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa, my replie (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - News- Record Article about Neil Mowbray (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Qualifications to Membership (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa (Correspondent), 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Correspondence, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Membership, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Chapter Dues (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Requirements for Membership, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Program, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- General Correspondence, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Letter of Invitation to Students (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Albert Clark Prize (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Member, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Write Up in Religious Studies News (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- spring, Notes from Journa, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Student Records, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Forms (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Information (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Membership, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Initiation (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Membership (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Majors and Minors List - GPA (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Honor Societies Program and Final Letter and Dinner Invitation (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Request for Certificates, Cor. with National Headquarters (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Shirley (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Local Ceremony- What Program Participants Need to Know (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Membership List- Students (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Biography of Speaker- Lorenzo Simpson (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Schaulemann- Introduction and Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Afternoon Tea (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa- Programs for local invitation (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Initiation Theta Alpha Kappa, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Instructions for Faculty Advisors Theta Alpha Kappa (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Need for National VP, Correspondence, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Theta Alpha Kappa Pins and Letters (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Amanda Bigelow (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Initiation Ceremony (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Forms for New Members (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Initiates- Signed Cards, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Program- Joint Init.Theta Alpha Kappa and Phi Sigma Tau, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Honor Societies Dinner- Phi Sigma Tau and Theta Alpha Kappa (Box 9, Folder 30)
- Classwork, 5
  - Leave Proposal to study Theology of Karl Barth (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Syllabus (Sp. 1990) and Description of Course (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Class Assignments and Syllabus (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - REL450 Course Work, REL/PHIL375 Syllabus, Barth Final Paper (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Readings, Syllabus 375 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Courses Taught and Descriptions (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Freshman Seminar in Humanities Proposal Papers (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Syllabus 302, Yale Male Course Syllabus (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Readings and Notes (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - What was Taught Each Day (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Class Lectures (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Readings and Notes (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Lectures and Notes for RELG203 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Lecture Notes and Readings (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - PHIL 240 Notes/Papers (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - REL 330 Notes/Papers (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - REL 320 Notes/Papers (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - REL 260 Notes/Papers (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Readings for Classes/Lectures (Box 12, Folder 6a)
  - Readings for Classes/Lectures (Box 12, Folder 6b)
  - Memorial Service- Dr. Miller, President Emeritus of JMU (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - My Curriculum Vitae (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous 2, 6
  - Faculty Activities Report (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - NEH Seminars (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Original Faculty Leave Proposal (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Resume, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Personnel Record and Course Outlines (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Activities Report (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Activities Report (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Department Tea (Box 13, Folder 8)
    4-4:45 February 24th Presidents Conference Room- Gibbons, confirmed 1994 February 4
  - Room- Gibbons, confirmed 1994 February 4 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Special Events- Thank You (Box 13, Folder 10)